software engineer radio episode 87
software components
[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet as your
radio Prince irrelevant and detailed
discussions and interviews on soft
engineering topics every 10 days thanks
to our audience and the partners listed
on our website for supporting the vodka
[Music]
welcome listeners to software
engineering radio here are a bunch of
announcements I want to make before we
go on with the actual content of this
episode we need your help please help
make su radio more widely known please
consider submitting su radio to sites
like Digg delicious slash dot reddit or
something we have those shortcut links
on each episode page this will help us
make su radio well more widely known so
more people can listen to the episodes
more fun for us because we have more
listeners more fun for those people
because they now know as your radio so
please help us make su radio more
well-known okay and here is the actual
episode so hello Mia hi markers well I
think this this episode is going to be
interesting we are going to discuss
software components and component
architecture and I think we both have
well at least about some aspects we have
both very specific opinions so I guess
this might be controversial at times
let's start with the definition of what
components are what do we understand by
the term component markers do you like
to start yeah why not I mean generally
component is a very much overloaded term
and the most generic definition is
basically a piece of software that is
somehow separately usable or separately
deployable if you build a system then
you have for example server component
and a client component this is very very
generic and in my personal view not very
useful but people do use it that way
however that's not the way we want to
discuss it as you'll see later another
definition is or another use I don't
know if there is a explicit definition
is you can find it in the in the
graphical user interfaces world and if
you listen to the Java Posse you will
probably know this discussion from from
from from the Naxal guy was his first
name I forget and he says basically
if you have classes in an object
programming language which also have
properties as well as events to which
you can register then that is what they
call components and that's in the
tradition of visual basic or Delphi they
all had those component libraries for
visual visual components typically two
to interactively compose user interfaces
so I guess then one one of the key
intentions is the reuse of software so
that is how it all started I believe in
in the 60s or 70s when the first
discussions arised
it's this this idea of being able as I
said to separately use something and
then of course to reuse something so it
should be as somehow well-defined subset
of functionality that is as the
generative programming people like to
say that's minimally read redundant and
maximally composable okay so it should
be composable with other components the
legal legal brick metaphor you can you
can assemble your system from stitching
components together and that's the
reason why there is such an emphasis on
interfaces on defined interfaces that
this component provides as well as those
that it requires right so basically the
context of a component in which
environment can this software component
and run what does it need absolutely so
that's one of the in my view really
important concepts of a component it
should declaratively specify as much of
its expected environment or end of its
provided services as possible why
declaratively how else would you do it I
mean you need some metadata that
describes it or you need very clear very
specific very very clearly defined let's
say idioms coding idioms so you can use
some kind of reflection a pair other
tooling to to inspect what a component
does or depends on otherwise you cannot
build tools that build or compose
applications by stitching together
components because the tool cannot find
out what a component does it needs to be
declarative or or based on metadata it's
the same thing so the metadata is the
key point and this is maybe I don't want
to stretch it too much because then we
into the model-driven discussion already
but another important point is the the
deployability
you should be able to deployed a
component in different environment so it
shouldn't well it shouldn't have any
implicit assumptions of the environment
all the environment dependencies must be
explicit so when you do deploy it in
some environment you can tell whether
it's gonna work or not
ideally statically that's that's at
least how I see it so if we go back to
other uses or definitions of component
the UML also has a notion of component
it's basically if you remember the UML
that's basically this rectangle with
these two small rectangles I think on
the left or right side and they consider
this more or less a deployment artifact
so they have this deployment view of
what a component is it's in my personal
opinion not very useful another thing
that comes to my mind is the discussion
about binary compatibility of the
interface right how important is that
I remember that IBM som discussion
really focused on this as well as comm
Microsoft con technology did is to still
relevant this discussion today I
personally don't see this as a defining
property of a component it well it
depends on how you compose your system
whether you want to be able to compose
the system by composing binary
components right then of course you have
to be able to have this binary plug
ability and then you need the metadata
somehow embedded in the binary
distributable but there is also a good
good use for components that are that
are more relevant during the
construction of software when you work
with source code in that case there is
no need for binary plug ability I would
say so in my practical experience
typically if you consider our components
as an architectural building block for
building systems then the binary plug
abilities is not not an issue whatsoever
okay and what did you want to say right
now when I disrupted you only I wanted
to say that there is also this kind of
classic definition by Clement Seversky
which I think you you
you looked up yeah this is one of the
definitions I looked up and there's a
one key property that he states is the
the that it shouldn't have persistent
state a component and so what what is
your opinion on that well again it it
what we will discuss that later in much
more detail but I think what a component
really is needs to be defined for a
specific system so there are customs
where the architects decide that
components are stateless and in that
case components obviously shouldn't have
state and also no persistence state but
there is also other systems where the
architects as well there there are
either stateless or stateful components
and there are components that might have
produced the state or non resistant
state or there are components which
themselves don't have state but they
manage access to a database which is
also some kind of state so I think that
the core is that it should be it should
be defined per project or per system in
some kind of well I don't
as you say we shouldn't get to them of
doing stuff too early some kind of meta
model right some some kind of definition
of what we consider a component is or
should be in a project and that can in
some projects include state and and not
include state and other projects that's
that's my understanding there so what we
realize is that it's really hard to give
a broad and general definition of the
term software component but the core is
I believe that you can use it separately
we use it separately and deploy it
separately with only explicit
dependencies absolutely and that's why
we don't this episode doesn't try to
define it we want to discuss how they're
used what their properties can be what
the typical variability is and and then
of course it's important that in a
specific project you actually define for
your project what you mean by a
component so why are components useful
you mention it already partly you yeah
why are components useful Marcus so of
course again this is my
my personal somewhat personal view there
is this traditional view where you say
components you know there is this
component marketplace where people
create components and then they are put
in this global repository where people
can then grab them and assemble their
systems from it I don't think this this
this idea of component based reuse has
ever really materialized I don't see
that happening and also it's kind of not
fashionable today anymore because today
we all do so I we reuse hosted services
so I think components are useful for
another reason if we build systems with
today's programming languages then those
programming languages are not able to
express architecture okay a programming
language expresses well implementation
code on a very fine grained granularity
you you have classes you have you have
procedures or methods or functions or
whatever and you have the
implementations of those but you cannot
easily say how your system is created or
or composed on an architectural level so
if you compare components with
object-oriented programming then I would
say that what classes are for the
implementation for the program is what
our components are for the architecture
so they are an architectures smallest
relevant independent building block so
if you build a system then you decompose
your system into components those
components have certain properties and
responsibilities and it's up to the
architect to define what those are and
we'll talk about that and inside the
components you might have whatever other
paradigm to to actually implement them
so components are the smallest
architectural irrelevant building block
foundation for architecture and what
kind of do you have other abstraction
levels besides components then or is
this basically everything a component
and you would have hierarchical
components or how do you orchestrate
this this is a very good question first
of all it's important to say and again
we will talk about that later there is
also another side to component which is
in most systems that I built
or see your work with a component is not
able to exist on its own it's somehow
managed ran or or or hosted by some kind
of container or environment that
provides additional services we all know
that from EJB or j2ee where you put an
enterprise javabean into a container and
it provides transactions and and
scalability and all that stuff you know
all that so that's it's kind of morning
so in that sense you don't just have
components you also have a container
that hosts them and it's up to the
platform architecture distinguish what
functionality goes into the components
and which of the functionality is
handled by the environment by the
container however I think your question
was getting somewhere else and I think
what you kind of probably really asked
was assuming you already factored out
this this container is everything else
components and there I would I would
argue yes because as I said before in a
project there can be you have to define
what a component is the comfort that can
be different kinds of components in a
project so so you could argue that
everything is components up to or should
say down to a certain level of
granularity once you get inside
components then you implement them using
whatever other technology and then of
course stuff isn't a component anymore
you already mentioned hierarchical
components I think we may be discussed
that later when we talk about what
components what which very abilities
they can have but that basically means
that you compose a component with
basically interconnected instances of
other components and then you have a
recursive structure and if you argue
that way then of course everything is a
component would you agree or do you see
it different no I mean what I learn is
that the way you use the term component
is you define it and in a specific
context and there's in the last
sentences you define it in the
architecture context how components can
help you to to structure and align and
basically provide a foundation of your
architecture so that you have
so that you are enabled to structure
your functionality
according to technical concepts it
allows you an easier mapping later to
technology this is what what I feel
exactly that's also one of the of the
core premises of the idea that a
component description if you say you
know it provides those services it uses
these other services and and maybe some
other metadata which we talk about later
it's technology independent on the
specification level and then you can
implement that component using oo or
functional programming or whatever and
and then you can use automated tools if
you want of course you don't have to to
then map that component to a certain
well environment or container or
technology and and that gives you a
degree of freedom between the component
it's metadata and the implementation on
one side and the technology choice
that's governed by non-functional
requirements well and hype I guess
before we go into further detail I like
to have one discussion that I really
needed to grasp and understand the
concept of components this is our
components do our direct components
require object orientation or what kind
of implementation technology concepts
classes whatever do I need to really
provide and implement components do I
have to use classes is a class already a
component this was pretty confusing for
me as a beginner some years ago in my
view components and object orientation
and classes are more or less unrelated
so let's let's elaborate a little bit on
this for example you can have a
component which is internal well ok so
assume you define a component using all
kinds of metadata and then the question
is how do you implement it one way to
implement it is you can take a class in
an object-oriented language and say this
class represents let's say the facade
the external view of the component it
implements the interface is the
component provides and it has using some
kinds of pattern
and idioms and and and framework stuff
it has a way of describing and accessing
the resources and and and all the other
environment things that it needs to
access in that case you you do use a
class as as an implementation artifact
of a component however inside that class
of course you might have fifteen other
classes and 287 objects and fifty-seven
methods so that's the Grandin Trent
granularity thing again however you can
also say that a component another kind
of component is implemented by business
rules right so you take a rule engine or
some kind of rule specification language
whatever it's the language of the day I
mean there are various open source tools
you can also use Prolog or whatever and
then the implementation is not
object-oriented at all and you can
implement it with with this other
technology so one of those I think key
realizations is that if you build a
system from components then there can be
different components some components are
let's say standard business logic
components they're implemented using or
others our rule components they're
implemented by a set of business rules
others our process components they're
implemented by people or BPMN or or some
other process description formalism
others are described state based
behavior in which case they published
events they can work with and then
internally there is a state machine that
is triggered and then like runs around
so in that sense oh is one way of
implementing components of or in other
words of providing the implementation
code for the functionality the component
wants to provide okay so there is no
direct relationship that is what I am
what ever was aiming at right mm-hm
so maybe another confusion is how do you
relate a component to a class versus to
an object like an object is an
instantiation close the class is only
the plan for this object for this kind
of object now what is a component of
this context is it more a plan or is it
more an instance yeah this is one of my
favorite topics because it creates
confusion in almost every project often
so here's my personal opinion a
component is lie
the class in the sense that it's
instantiate able so there is components
and there is component instances there
is no other word for it in my view and
the component instances are instances of
the component like objects are instances
of classes so they provide values for
properties they you know whatever
instantiation means in practice this
also somewhat depends on the definition
of a component however there are systems
where there is always only one instance
of a component in which case it is kind
of pointless to distinguish components
and component instances let's look at an
example let's look at an embedded system
and you want to describe a vehicle with
components a personal car and you want a
component that controls the the window
right the electric window is you can
press a button and the component runs on
engine some electrical engine that motor
that the drives out the window or down
then you have a component which you
would call window controller okay and it
for example knows how to talk to the
electrical motor that controls the
window and maybe it has an input that is
feed a fed from some kind of switch that
is triggered by the window if it if it
reaches the top position so now a car
has four windows so it's kind of obvious
what you do you define your window
thingie component and then you have four
instances of that one for front left
front right back left and back right
okay so in that case is kind of obvious
also if you have hierarchical components
then it's well it's probably not obvious
because that's where the discussions are
all the time but I think it's if you
think about it it's obvious that if you
compose a component from other component
like things inside then these are
component instances because if you look
at the car as a whole in our example you
could describe the cars software itself
as a component which is then kind of
instantiated for each car we actually
built and then of course each of them
each of the things inside a component
are of course themselves instances it's
also like an object orientation if you
define a class then the class doesn't
contain other classes it
contains objects right variables which
are basically objects and and the
behavior or the functionality the
implementation of a class is composed by
stitching together objects not classes I
mean yes there are in the classes in
languages like Java but that's forget
that for a moment the classical
object-oriented programming
defines new types by connecting
instantiated other types and writing
algorithms around it and it's the same
thing and in components component is
something that can be instantiated and
then connected with other components so
now that we had some some of the basics
why don't we get into more details and
so what what is really necessary what
should a component specify what should
the metadata contain and specify for the
component yeah let me let me step back
like a half step and that is assume we
have defined what a component is how do
we describe a system that is made from
components and I can i think it's
obvious from the discussion we had
before about the instantiation stuff
that a component based system is
basically a system that is made up of
connected instances of components so if
you define a system what you do is you
take you're a bunch of components you
have in your library you instantiate
them and then you connect them and the
connection thing is what I want to get
it a connection is basically if some
component says I provide the service and
the other component says I require that
service then you should establish a
connection a wire or a connector between
instances of those components so that
the one instance of that one component
knows which of those other instances
actually does provide the specific
service it requires at runtime so that's
that's important so if you describe a
system you have typically several view
points one view point describes the
components we just discussed that with
whatever properties they have see in
five minutes another view point
describes the composition which is
instance instances of those components
and how they are interconnected
and then a third viewpoint typically
describes the deployment or the system
view where you say I want this component
to run on some kind of server machine
another component on some other client
machine well I should have said
component instance sorry and and then
you you also map them to certain
execution infrastructures like whatever
j2ee or EJB whatever so these are the
kind of three main viewpoints and that
that kind of leads into the discussion
of what metadata it needs if you want to
describe a system the metadata needs to
needs to describe the components it
needs to describe the instances and
their connections and it needs to
describe the allocation of the instances
to execution containers and hardware
that was kind of the system view I think
your question was targeted towards what
what a component as a type specification
should include in its specification yeah
so maybe we could differentiate between
the absolute minimum the core and some
some typical or nice to have or common
properties that components in today's
technologies typically specify and
require yep so the minimum is the
interfaces or services it provides and
those it requires so that allows you
simple dependency checking so you know a
system is only able to work with if all
if all required services of all the
instances you have are basically
satisfied by provided services from
other instances one way of deciding
whether this is minimal or not is simply
to look at existing technologies and if
you look at typical today's dependency
injection frameworks like spring as the
most prominent one in the Java world and
I guess spring dotnet and Internet then
then that's exactly what they do
you you describe the services you
provide by having a class that simply
implements certain interface and you
describe the services you require by
using certain dependency injection
conventions either with setter methods
or constructor parameters
so to recap I think the minimum is
described
which interfaces you require and which
interfaces you provide since we talk
about interfaces well if you listen to
us discussing here this probably sounds
to you a little bit like the typical RPC
kind of thing right like our BA object
to something so an interface is a
collection of methods you can call
synchronously blocking and so on and
it's important to address that that's
not the case an interface is simply as a
way of specifying how to interact with a
component and such an interaction can
either be synchronous message call a
sorry synchronous procedure call based
in which case you have typical
interfaces as you know them from Java or
kora or whatever or language and but you
can also have a message driven system in
which case a component defines a bunch
of messages it can understand and other
messages it kind of sends out publishes
as its interface so in that case an
interface is a bunch of messages and
maybe a specification of how these
messages relate this is typically known
as interaction paradigms message
interaction paradigms so you say things
like this is a request response paradigm
where you accept the request message and
then reply by one response message or
there's another paradigm the
publish/subscribe where somebody sends
your subscription message message and
then you send periodic updates of
whatever thing you want to tell these
other clients periodically so this is
different message interaction paradigm
so so an interface has to specify those
and this is exactly something that the
architect would typically define at the
beginning of a project what kind of
interaction the components should have
and I guess it also depends on a
technology but very much on the famous
non-functional requirements of the
project whether it's highly asynchronous
or whether synchronous invocations are
sufficient absolutely and it's not so
much necessarily technology dependent
because you can simulate like RPC style
stuff through message oriented
middleware and also you can have
asynchronous and and more decoupled
things using things like carbon so it's
more really what as you
it's this this the work and the
architect understands the requirements
understands non-functional requirements
and then people discuss and discuss and
decide ok our system should be primarily
message oriented in which case you will
define components whose interfaces are
as I said those those message
interaction schemes so it's as minimum
Orestes already some extended set of
property the definition of interfaces is
minimum you well how else do you specify
something that it does or it depends on
if you look at the message oriented
world then I would say formally defining
interaction paradigms with protocol
state machines or something that's
beyond the minimum okay what else
anything else before the for the minimum
specification I would no I don't think
so I mean for the minimum its the
interfaces that provided and required
ones right and everything else is then
depending under the context on the
project the interfaces are independent
of components right so you don't say a
component owns some kind of interface
because that would mean nobody else
could use this interface and it's kind
of pointless
so components or interfaces are contract
specifications that are their own that
they live on their own and components
can then say I provide this interface
and others say I require this interface
let's let's look a little bit at how you
can give more semantic meaning somehow
to components you said before or you ask
the question is everything a component
and I said kind of yes and assume a
typical enterprise system you have stuff
that happens on the client that has a
visual representation other stuff
happens on the server and and typically
provides database access other stuff
also happens on the server and does some
business logic um computations or
calculations or algorithmic stuff so the
question is can you distinguish those
and how do you manage dependencies
because typically what you say is yes
it's possible that a GUI component can
access a remote business logic component
it's also allowed that a business logic
component access a accesses a database
management data something component but
not the other way around
this is the typical layer
bring stuff which we know we all know
that layering is a very good thing for
for big systems and one way you can
easily merge that with the idea of
components is that you associate each
component or each component type with a
layer you say you do have three kinds of
components GUI components business logic
components and database access
components and then you define what the
allowed dependencies are like GUI can
depend on business logic business logic
can depend on database but nothing else
and then you can easily check when you
specify or build a concrete system you
can use some kind of constraint checker
that says hey you have just violated
your your own rules which is that the
dependencies can only go at this
direction and another property that
comes to mind is versioning I mean yeah
we discussed in the beginning that the
reuse is so important and now you start
off with your project
use the component the first time now
every system evolves typically and
what's in version - how can you properly
differentiate between the new generation
the new version of a component how can
you make sure that your system really
uses consistently the new component
version little technologies have in my
mind in my understanding versioning
support built in yes I know that net has
has some versioning support and and some
IBM some in the past did have but Kaba
didn't really provide good versioning
support usable versioning support and
the problem with versioning is of course
compatibility right if you want to make
sure that if you have a new version of a
component that the environment of that
component can still use the new version
without kind of crashing so you can want
a pluggable company plug plug-and-play
right you want to replace an existing
version of a component with a new
version and the system should still work
you want to have seamless upgrades if
possible yes that is something that
users are just so used today well I
don't download every new component of
this new piece of software provide a
consistance upset that then install
deployed will work together and not fail
because of missing interfaces yeah like
that so let's think about first of all
what it means to be compatible it means
that a new version of a component
provides all the services of the old
component and maybe more and that it
does not depend on additional
environment right so because the system
might not provide that environments you
cannot plug it in so that's one of the
constraints and if you if you if you
look at it a little bit more
semantically and think about pre and
post conditions which is by the way also
something you can associate with
interfaces and components if you want
then this means that the precondition of
some operation or interaction must be
the same one as in the old version or
others because it can handle the old
stuff and more stuff and the post
condition is either the one the post
condition from the old one or a more
specific post condition so you or the
preconditions together and you end the
post conditions together so that's more
to semantic view but the key to making
versioning possible is primarily
metadata right so what you want to do is
you want to say that this component here
is a new version of that other component
and then if you have sufficient metadata
you can again run a constraint checker
that verifies that this new component
actually does provide all the services
of the old one plus optional new
services and that it does not have
additional environment dependencies so
it's all about metadata once you have
the metadata you can run the checks and
then you can statically verify that if
you replace this component with its new
version it will work but there are no
syntactical conflicts this mandigal
are always a bit harder and here you
need conventions or rules or stuff to
fill that in into the metadata to make
that to represent it somehow all the pre
and post conditions stuff right
if you define the pre and post
conditions with an interface and not
with a component then if you have a new
version of a component implement the
same interface the same pre and post
conditions apply so it cannot violate
the semantics now we all know that this
scribing semantics with pre and post
conditions is not necessarily trivial
and that you cannot describe all
semantics but that's typically also not
needed in every project but if there are
certain aspects of the component
semantics that are critical to be
compatible in subsequent versions well
then come up with metadata for it it's
not possible to define all kinds of
semantics with metadata in general but
for certain kinds of semantics that is
important for your system you can come
up with metadata or formal notations to
describe them it's not not rocket
science well I've done it so so it's
possible there are other stuff for
example something that's kind of obvious
is configuration parameters if you look
at executables in in an operating system
then they have command line parameters
so the same with components a component
can have a bunch of configuration
parameters which it reads at runtime to
adapt its behavior dynamically somehow
and typically what happens is that the
component defines the parameters and the
component instance once it's invented or
deployed provides the values for those
kind of obvious but it's very important
another one is ports that's kind of not
that trivial but considered the
following thing consider a component
that the kind of stupid example always
have is a component which transfers data
from one database to another so it needs
to connect to two databases and assume
the database thing is also a component
then it would have basically a required
service required interface it would say
I need the database interface in order
to do something however it doesn't need
one of those it needs two of them
because one is the source database in
the other one is the target database so
it's often not enough to say that a
component provides a certain service or
use a certain service it needs to be
able to distinguish different roles of
using that service kind of communication
endpoints and that's what you do with a
port a port is simply a named
communication endpoint of a component
which is associated with an interface
and then you can have several ports with
the same interface and they can be
connected separately with other
instances another thing that
goes more into the interaction with
container or some hosting environment is
some of the internal behavior is a
component single-threaded or is it
threat safe does it have a life cycle
does it need to be activated can it be
shut down by the environment can it be
passivated what do you do if you restart
can it be killed
dust have state is it stateless stateful
all these things might need to be
specified depending of course on your
concrete component definition that's the
whole point of this discussion you might
have to specify these things so the
environment can can work with AB
sensibly another thing is how you want
to wire the component instances are you
able to say statically when you define
the system that component instance a
talks to some other component instance B
or should this be resolved at runtime
like I do have component instance a and
it needs to talk to somebody who
provides this in that interface and you
can resolve that dynamically at runtime
that's what naming services and trader
services in carbon and other
environments do so in incorporating or
distinguishing between static wiring and
dynamic wiring is an important thing the
last thing I want to mention here in
this in this discussion is well the bad
last thing but it's it's something
called replicated state when I was at a
customer recently they were building or
well they thought they were building a
system that was basically based on
message passing so they had components
and interfaces and interfaces will
consist of consisted of messages that
went into components or out of
components the thing we discussed before
however after discussing of a while we
noticed well it's not really that they
use message passing what they really
have is a shared replicated state right
so there is some state in the system
which is provided by certain component
which is updated by a certain component
and that there are other components
which read that state so the the
intention of what you want to really do
is you want to define that state you
want to define who updates it and how
often it is updated and you want to know
who reads this state and how often it is
read so that my customer people were so
much in this message oriented world that
they were kind of trying to Express
replicated stayed with messages and of
course you have to specify all kinds of
things you need messages that update the
state incrementally or do a complete
refresh and all that stuff if they
change their perception from message
oriented to replicate its state then
it's much easier you just defined the
data structure and you say who publishes
it and who needs it and how often you
want to be updated so we changed the
metamodel that described the component
we we changed what we mean by a
component to include a way of specifying
that it creates and/or uses certain
shared state and that made the
specification of the system when it
reduced the size of the specification
significantly because you didn't have to
deal with this low-level message
exchange stuff the abstraction was not
shared State so what I want to say is
certain component architectures might
also have the notion of shared state as
part of their definition what a
component is ok that was long so what
what other topic should we discuss for
example the environment that you
mentioned before what kind of services
does a typical component environment
also called application server very
often does it provide again of course it
depends on the on the domain in which
you're working typical services are is
resource management access to all kinds
of resources like threads network
connections files whatever and as it
happens there is a book that talks about
resource management I think you know it
well yes I know it well
coincidence so obviously Michel is the
co-author of this book and it's about
resource management and how to
efficiently manage resources and that's
something the environment often does do
you want to elaborate on that a little
bit
yeah it's about all the strategies that
you need for efficient resource
management as Mark has already started
it's resource can be anything in that
context it's a thread a piece of memory
or even processing time that you want to
efficiently use and and share
potentially and so there in this book
there's a set of patterns that describe
how to interact with resaw
if you have a certain focus on on
individual non-functional requirements
like if you focus on real time
properties you will choose a different
set of patterns that avoid for example
on-demand loading and load everything
upfront or if you focus on scalability
you will pay the penalty of not being so
fast and so efficient but you will be
able to scale your system to a much
higher number of user servers of
whatever your your scalability factor is
of course we had an episode back in the
day in the SA radio podcast and we'll
link to it so well yeah so that's that's
one big thing in general it's the job of
the container to manage the resources
the life cycle of the component
instances and well the access of the
component instances to those resources
and again as you said these are
different depending on the domain and
what you really want to do examples
include the stuff you already mentioned
things like virtualization so making
sure that the component looks as if it's
still available but in reality it's kind
of paged out and reactivated on demand
naming identification is another thing
that that components get unique
identifiers and you can address them if
they have stayed remote access to
components this is the application
server thing there is by the way another
book which we talked about in previous
episode transaction management error
handling logging so these are all the
things that that that an application
server or component container typically
does what you could say is that
components handle the functional
requirements containers handle the
non-functional requirements and the
metadata that describes the component
makes sure that the container knows what
to do with a component and on topic that
we didn't hit on so far but is really
exciting and sometimes causes long
discussions and projects is the
differentiation between a component and
the service like in service orientation
today like some claimed well we don't do
component oriented software development
or component based software development
we do now service-oriented software
development now
it's your round markers first of all in
order to distinguish the two we would
have to be able to define both of them
concisely which we already noticed we
kind of failed four components and as
everybody knows it's impossible for so
that's the first problem so I think
there is one thing that that is kind of
important and that is that in component
oriented development you typically talk
about and that's not it doesn't have to
be like that but that's traditionally
how it's viewed if you want to reuse
something what you do is you you grab
that component and integrate it into
your system basically by running it on
your application server slash container
in SOA it's a bit different what you do
is you basically say there is these
services running all over the world or
all over the enterprise and if you want
to use it you just remotely connect to
it but of course I mean I don't know
this is kind of not a hard distinction
personally I think so I is primarily a
bunch of hype if you look at least at
the technological stuff in many ways you
can argue that service-oriented
architecture is components done right or
it's basically the same thing or it's a
password for it I have a really hard
time distinguishing the two one thing is
that in so are you have this explicit
distinction between like services and
then business processes that that work
on those services but I mean in a in a
well-defined component based system you
might have components which encapsulate
process and other components that
encapsulate more basic services and then
one calls the other so in that sense
it's the same thing I honestly have a
very hard time distinguishing the two
and I personally think the component
oriented view with the metadata stuff we
discussed above is more grounded in
reality than some of the so our hype
there's one thing I want to I want to
talk about briefly and that is service
oriented architecture primarily looks at
how a system provides a certain sir
for example if you look at the WSDL
description of web services which is
obviously one way of building as a ways
all but not the only one then a WSDL one
point X specification only defines the
services somebody provides it doesn't
define what somebody depends on and that
is because what you do define is
actually a service and the service is
really just something somebody else can
use you don't define a component which
is something that provides the service
and uses other services so I think the
best distinction I could come up with is
that components can be seen as an
implementation technology for SOA a
service is basically a bunch of things
that others can use that you provide and
the component is actually the entity
that uses a service or provides a
service something that pops into my mind
is the SCA yeah the service component
architecture which is basically what you
just said makes it more explicit and
actually provides a programming model
that exactly represents this view right
so this leads us into the technologies
into the example technologies SCA the
service component architecture is is I
think a very very good component
architecture and of course labeled on
the ZOA because that's today's hype du
jour but I think the idea there is of
course that you define component types
you can instantiate them you can connect
them components can be structured
hierarchically they do use some other
terms for some of those things they have
modules and stuff but it's basically
your hierarchically a hierarchically
structured component model with then of
course the ability to express or expose
services in ways that are accessible to
so our systems like typically WSDL or or
some of these other things so it's it's
a rather new standard I forget what the
institution is that defines it and they
have created a new institution for it I
forget what it's called it's certainly
something to look at when I saw it first
I was actually really happy because I
saw many of my own preachings in it
because it was the first component well
at least more or less recent component
standard that looked at hierarchical
deconstructs
and in some of these things and and
distinguish between deployment and and
logical instantiation and composition
versus types so I think they've done a
lot of things right okay so what what
other technologies we had previous to
this recording a discussion and there I
asked you what technology provides the
bare minimum of a component model and
you answered spring so so why is that
right and it's not just spring it's
basically all dependency injection
containers because as we elaborated
before we said that the minimum that you
need to do as a component is specify
what you provide which interfaces or
services and what you expect from your
environment and that is exactly what the
spring Corps does it provides a
dependency injection framework the
container is basically it doesn't do
anything else so it's it's kind of
somewhat of a stretch to call spring a
container but it does manage
dependencies in in both ways and that's
a good thing it also does provide
certain non-functional support for
non-functional requirements using spring
chorus aspect orientation mechanism so
you can basically deploy interceptors
around component instances that then for
example provide remote access to a
components interfaces or do some
transaction stuff so in that sense I
would say spring car with its dependency
injection is the absolute minimum using
its AO features you can even add
non-functional requirements support or
well support for container handled
non-functional stuff using Springs I
would say that's kind of the minimum so
if you rate spring and spring like
containers as the minimum how would you
rate each a be calm and Kaba as some of
the basically old guys today well let's
look at each of them separately each a B
as we all know is a direct competitor to
spring the more current ETA B releases
three EGP three specifically is is well
the spring guys say it's not up to what
spring can do of course each of these
guys say did the opposite but it's I
think it's it's obvious that EJB
independent of the version was one of
the prime
first and widely deployed component
infrastructures at least in the
enterprise world where you really had an
explicit container and you had metadata
description they call it deployment
descriptors and and you had your
components were implementation of pure
business logic yes you had all those
lifecycle interfaces and all that crap
you had to write it was early people
make mistakes
spring improved on that but I think that
general idea is is there and it did work
well comm is it's somewhat of a welcome
comm isn't calm there are many aspects
there is calm there's decom there's calm
plus and basically it's a it's a
relatively early component model it had
binary compatibility or applicability
and I don't know it's it is very complex
it's it the specifications with all
those goods and all that crap it's not
very nice it's hard to use it's tough to
use don't box kind of one of the Guru's
who used this stuff and who wrote about
this stuff once called it too complex so
it was an old model it was basically the
direct competitor to koruba decom in
case of remote communication the carpet
isn't really a component model Carbaugh
is first and foremost a remote
communications infrastructure and the
kaabah component model added a container
to it where you could predefined certain
life cycle well it the container came
with certain predefined life cycle
schemes like I don't know entity
components which had stayed and
stateless services which I know stayed
and and then you could basically add
metadata to your karma objects and and
then the container would handle them
according to that metadata so karma
components isn't used very wide widely
it's used in the defense world quite a
bit but not that much
EJ B certainly is on it's well I'm not
sure I wouldn't say it's on its way out
but it's not it's not the only kid on
the block anymore because spring really
takes away quite a bit of its market
share so that the technologies we talked
about in the couple of last couple of
minutes are the traditional ones some
are historic some are traditional some
are still current but it's important to
point out that many of them still
somewhat minimal you for example in in
most of them there is no out-of-the-box
way to describe certain different
component types many don't support the
notion of ports we mentioned before the
support for describing different
metadata with regards to threading and
active versus passive and stuff is very
limited many can't have events you
cannot in some you cannot distinguish
between static and dynamic wiring
replicated state is something they all
don't have I'm a big fan of actually
defining my own component model for a
given project because none of those
existing standards I think that's what I
need and and more specifically I cannot
easily extend it and that's more
important so let's briefly look at some
maybe lesser-known component oriented
technologies one is the windows
communication foundation technology
formerly known as indigo it's basically
a message oriented system but they also
have components which define their
interfaces as a set of messages they
they consume and provide and then you
can basically define message queues
which have which handles certain
different properties you can have
transactional queues and I think they
call these links endpoints so that's
actually a very interesting and and
really modern and actually nicely done
component infrastructure I think another
one is AUTOSAR the automotive systems
architecture standard it's basically a
component based middleware for
automotive embedded software in case you
don't know a typical personal vehicle
these days contains 50 to 100 computers
which are connected with various bus
systems can bus most bus and and and
other bus systems and of course you need
to have software in the car that that
works efficiently and that it's
distributed and then you have all kinds
of variants of cars and special
equipment and you have to dynamic well
not dynamically but flexibly composed
the overall system from components and
the auto sort of thing is a standard
they're relatively new I think 2003 was
when it came out and and the interesting
thing about it is that it's actually an
embedded system so the stuff we talked
about is not limited to big iron
enterprise stuff you can use it in the
embedded world of course you have to
implement things differently you don't
have this big application server you
maybe have a modular embedded operating
system which you then configure so it
can handle the kinds of components you
want to deploy on it another thing that
I heard recently about is Android the
the Google mobile operating system
that's currently hyped quite a bit and
without going into too much detail we'll
put a link to a Google developer pad
podcast episode into the show notes it's
also component oriented they again
invented certain terminology they talked
about intent and intent receivers and
another stuff I don't remember all of it
but it certainly is component oriented
intent and and has many of the
characteristics we talked about before
the last thing I want to mention is
singularity that's actually really cool
in case some of the discussions above
sounded a little bit like well hmm it
sounds like components our programs and
application servers and containers are
basically operating systems yes there is
a relation there so Microsoft has a
research project called singularity
where they have built a completely new
operating system using this metaphor of
components and metadata and verifiable
metadata and and static security and
code analysis and and all that stuff
extremely cool and as it happens the
next episode of se radio will feature an
interview with the primary researcher
who leads the project at Microsoft Galen
hunt and we'll talk there about how
singularity kind of implements this
notion of components it's one of the
reasons why we are having this component
episode now in se radio so because this
is a good foundation for the for the
singularity episode next week okay
anything that we missed well that we
have these esoteric questions which we
maybe there is one thing that we didn't
talk about yet and that is our component
models a domain model for programming
and I think this is really a very nice
analogy if you look at today's hype
around to mind driven development and
domain-specific languages and and some
of that stuff where people say you
should understand your domain and then
build languages around your domains you
can efficiently express algorithm
structures and and
simply stuff in that domain then if you
consider software architecture the
domain which is what you should do if
you're a software architect then the
stuff we talked about the component
stuff is basically a way of defining a
domain-specific language for describing
your architecture and by doing that by
defining the language you understand you
you formally define what a component is
and what properties it has and how it
works and how you specify it and if you
then use that language to define a
specific system you have well this is
basically a sentence in in the language
you define the architecture of a
specific system as opposed to the
language which specifies the
abstractions you use for building
systems so kind of a buzzword that I
like to establish here is like
architecture as language that instead of
trying to write documents that describe
an architecture what you maybe should do
is get together with your with your
stakeholders and and as you try to
understand the architecture literally
define a language define a grammar using
a suitable tooling that allows you to
describe instances of that architecture
certain systems based on that
architecture and by trying to define
that language what you do is you refine
your understanding of the architecture
and and formalize what the architect or
what the capabilities of the building
blocks
ie components are and I've used this in
a number of project and it's amazing how
how how well this works because it
allows you to express systems
independent of technology and it removes
all kinds of misunderstandings because
if people say well you know what what is
a component you can point them to the
grammar and say you know component is
something as you can see that provides a
bunch of interfaces that requires an
other set of interfaces that is single
threaded or multi-threaded you can
specify that it can
I don't know produce events and it has
configuration parameters so formalizing
your architecture into a language is a
very very powerful concept and
components and their metadata
descriptions are a really really good
starting point and I hope that this
episode gave you a bunch of ideas about
what a component can have
in its metadata and its functionality we
also have a bunch of slides that we'll
put into the show notes okay I think
this wasn't perfect and for this episode
thank you Marcus thank you bye bye
bye
[Music]
thanks for listening to software
engineering radio if you want more
information about the podcast and all
the other episodes visit our website at
SE - radio dotnet if you want to support
us you can donate to the SU radio team
by on the website or you can advertise
for su radio for example by clicking on
the dick reddit delicious and /not
buttons to contact the team lease an
email to team and SI radio net or if
it's specific to an episode please use
the comments facility on the website so
other people can read and react to your
comments this episode of software
engineering radio as well as all other
episodes are licensed under Creative
Commons license please see the website
for details thanks to Charlie Crowell
and the pot site Music Network for the
music used in this show the song is
called Vegas hard rock shuffle